Guide to the Edith Kramer Papers MC.215
New York University Archives
- Series II: Photographs and Slides, 2.5 Linear Feet In 2 record cartons and one manuscript box.
  - Drawing Watercolor Edith Kramer's Drawings and Watercolor Slides, 1972, Undated (Box 5, Folder 63)
  - Sonia Patient Artwork Slides, Undated (Box 5, Folder 64)
  - Demonstration II Artwork Slides, 1965-1966, Undated (Box 5, Folder 65)
  - Sublimination Patient Artwork Slides & The Royal Library Slides, Undated (Box 5, Folder 66)
  - Egg Tempera Edith Kramer Artwork Slides, 1975-1997 (Box 5, Folder 67)
  - Decarly Usaut Early Edith Kramer Artwork Slides, 1949-1990 (Box 5, Folder 68)
  - Jackson Patient Artwork Slides, Undated (Box 5, Folder 69)
  - [Redacted] Patient Artwork Slides, 1969, Undated (Box 5, Folder 70)
  - Herman Patient Artwork Slides, 1968-1969, Undated (Box 5, Folder 71)
  - Jacoby Spring 72 Patient Artwork Slides, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 72)
  - Jewish Guild/ Carciss at Guild Artwork Slides, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 73)
  - L&W Blondie Patient Artwork Slides, 1959-1960 (Box 5, Folder 74)
  - Gabe 1978 Patient Artwork Slides, 1964-1965 (Box 5, Folder 74)
  - Pendergast & Misc. Wiltwyck Patient Artwork Slides, Undated (Box 5, Folder 76)
  - Late 70s & 80s Edith Kramer Artwork Slides, 1979-1987 (Box 5, Folder 77)
  - Ray 64/65 Patient Artwork Slides, 1964-1965 (Box 5, Folder 78)
  - Chapters 1,8, and 9 Note,s Copies, and Photographs, Undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Chapter 7 and 10 Copies with Notes and Photographs, Undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Chapters 11, 12, and 16 Notes, Copies, and Photographs, Undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Chapters 15, 18, and 20 Notes, Copies, and Photographs, Undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Edith's Photos (1), 1925-1993, Undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Edith's Photos (2), 1997-1998, Undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Photograph of Friedl Dicker-Brandeis, Undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Photo Negatives and Contact Sheets, Undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Dwayne and Friends Photos and Artwork (9W), Undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Patient Artwork Photographs, 1965-1968 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Patient Artwork Photographs, 1964-1966, Undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Patient Artwork Photographs, 1965-1969, Undated (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Patient Artwork Photographs, 1966-1968, Undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Photographs of Unidentified Children, Undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Photographs from Edith Kramer Exhibit, 1997 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Mountain Cabin Studio Photos, Grundlsee Austria, 2004, Undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Photos of Carliss, Blind Child in Claymaking, Undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Edith Kramer Artwork Prints, 1980-2002 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Photographs of Edith Kramer's Artwork, 1984-2001 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Black and White Photographs of Edith Kramer's Paintings and Sculptures, 1938-1992 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Edith Kramer Artwork Photos, Postcards, and Prints, 1972-1992, Undated (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Invitation Photos, 1994-1996 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Photograph of Edith Kramer painting in a field, Undated (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Subway mural photographs, Undated (Box 13, Folder 17, Box 14, Folder 7, Flat-file-folder 6)
- Series III: Personal Papers, 1 Linear Feet in one record carton.
  This series consists mainly of personal correspondence, most of which is in English and some of which is in German. There is also information Edith Kramer compiled about the Bosket family, a family of professional interest to Kramer, as well as short, handwritten autobiographical narratives written by Edith Kramer. The series also contains a number of Edith Kramer's date books.
  - Pocket Date Books, 1949-1951 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Official Class Roll Book, 1984-1991 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Assignments & Dates to Remember, 1981-1982 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Datebooks, 1998-2001 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Datebooks, 2001-2006 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: A-C, 1949-1999 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: D-G, 1949-2000 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: H-J, 1938, 1992, Undated (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: K-M, 1950-2002 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: N-P, 1948,1973,1995 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: Q-S, 1949-1993 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: T-Z, 1950-1996 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence: General A-I, 1949-2003 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence: General J-P, 1950, 1990, 1996, Undated (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence: General Q-Z, 1948-1985 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence: General- Unisgned, 1949-1972 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence: Dr. Bernard (mentor), 1950 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence: Ingred B. Hansson, 1998-2006 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence: Von Ewer Schwurstenn Heidrun, 2001-2003 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence: Peter Heller, 1986-1996 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence: Jeanne/J, 1945-1998 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence: Lena, 1981-1992 (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence: Liesl, Undated, 1946, 1951 (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence: Nizie, 1949-1952 (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence: Emily Nelligan, Undated (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence: Hazel & Mark Peper, 1948-1949 (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence: Sandra Pine, 1980 (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence: Heidrun Pupp, Undated (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence: Sally, 1948-1950 (Box 8, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence: Schocken Books, 1962-1975 (Box 8, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence: Elizabeth Sifton, 1948-1950 (Box 8, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence: Sigga, 1985-1999 (Box 8, Folder 32)
  - Correspondence: Bernice Thompson, 1947-1948 (Box 8, Folder 33)
  - Correspondence: Russerln Dein, 1936-1949 (Box 8, Folder 34)
  - Correspondence: Elinor Ulman, 1958-1967 (Box 8, Folder 35)
  - Correspondence: Random/Assorted, 1993, 1999, Undated (Box 8, Folder 36)
  - Papers on William Butch Bosket Sr., 1980-1983 (Box 8, Folder 37)
  - Papers on William James Bosket Jr., 1987-1992 (Box 8, Folder 38)
  - Papers from All God's Children: The Bosket Family, 1993-1995 (Box 8, Folder 39)
  - Unidentified Artwork, 1957, Undated (Box 8, Folder 40)
  - Litte Red School House: A Chronicle of 75 Years, 1996 (Box 8, Folder 41)
  - Edith Kramer Artwork Papers and Catalogue, 1938-1996 (Box 8, Folder 42)
  - Miscellaneous Manuscript Pages and Notes, Undated (Box 8, Folder 43)
  - Art Therapy in a Children's Community Noted Book Jacket Manuscript, Undated (Box 8, Folder 44)
  - Edith Kramer's Handwritten Autobiographical Narratives, Undated (Box 8, Folder 45)
  - Patient's Handwritten Narrative with Contributions from Edith Kramer, Undated (Box 8, Folder 46)
  - Assorted Mailings from Art and Art Therapy Associations, 1975, 1994, 1998, Undated (Box 8, Folder 47)
  - Miscellaneous Notes and Document, 1941-1985 (Box 8, Folder 48)
- Series IV: Audiovisual Material
  This series consists of audiovisual materials and electronic records. Included within this series are CDs of photographs of Edith Kramer's artwork and of her trips to Austria. There are also video recordings of lectures from her course "Psychodynamic Processes in Art Therapy." There are also several audio recordings that include interviews of Kramer and recordings of presentations she gave at meetings of the American Art Therapy Association.
  Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
  Not all the audiovisual materials in this series have been digitized, and audiovisual materials may not be used in their original formats. Please contact the University Archives to gain access to these materials. Be aware that it may take several weeks to have audiovisual materials digitized for access.
  The videocassettes depicting Edith Kramer's course "Psycho Dynamic Processes in Art Therapy" have already been digitized. Please contact the Archives for access.
  - Edith Kramer Artwork, 2010, undated; 1 CD-ROM (Box 9, Disc 1)
    This disc contains over 200 digital images of Edith Kramer's works of art.
  - Edith Kramer Biographical Photographs, 2010, undated; 1 CD-ROM (Box 9, Disc 2)
  - Edith Kramer Weiss Galley Photographs, 2010, undated; 1 CD-ROM (Box 9, Disc 3)
  - Edith Kramer Psychodynamic Processes In Art Therapy Lectures, 2006; 10 videocassettes
    Ten lectures on Psychodynamic Process in Art Therapy.
    - Original Recording (Box 9, Vhs 4)
    - Original Recording (Box 9, Vhs 5)
    - Original Recording (Box 9, Vhs 6)
    - Original Recording (Box 9, Vhs 7)
    - Original Recording (Box 9, Vhs 8)
    - Original Recording (Box 9, Vhs 9)
    - Original Recording (Box 9, Vhs 10)
    - Original Recording (Box 9, Vhs 11)
    - Original Recording (Box 9, Vhs 12)
    - Original Recording (Box 9, Vhs 13)
    - Access Copies (Box Shared University Archives 112, Dvd 9:34-9:43)
  - Edith Kramer Lecture on her Work at the New York Transit Museum, March 1, 1994
    This recording features a talk Edith Kramer gave at the New York Transit Museum on March 1, 1994. Her lecture was a feature of her own exhibition that was on display there at the time, and a celebration at the beginning of Women's History Month. The exhibition featured subway-related art Kramer had created between 1940 and 1994. She discusses her artwork and life in New York City.
    The event is apparently sparsely attended as the Museum Curator Tom Harrington says in his opening remarks, "the world's situation has kept the crowd down to just a few." He does not specify what situation he means, but it is possible he is referring to the shooting attack on a bus full of Orthodox Jewish students that had taken place on the Brooklyn Bridge that morning, which would eventually result the death of 16-year-old Ari Halberstam. At the time of this recording, the shooter, Rashid Baz, was still at large.
    Art.; subway trains; Subway stations.; Subways in art; Subways.; Artists.; Art -- Study and teaching.; Art therapy.; New York Transit Museum; Kramer, Edith, 1916-2014; New York (State). Metropolitan Transportation Authority
    - Original Recording (Box 9, Audiocassette 14)
    - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 113, Cd 10:26)
  - Das Lied Ist Aus/Elisabeth Neuman-Viertel, May 1988
    "Das Lied ist aus" is the original title of a 1930 German film. The title translated into English as The Song Is Ended. Elisabeth Neuman-Viertel was a German actress. While she was active at that time, she was not in the cast. Neuman-Viertel was active at the time of these recordings and was in a 1988 film entitled, Wie kommt das Salz ins Meer? The beginnings of both sides is identical, a female voice speaking in German fading out as the sound of goose-stepping soldiers fades in. Based on this identical content, the consecutive dates and the serial notation of "parts 3 and 4," these are probably recordings of two episodes of a radio show of some kind, possibly focusing on 1930's German cinema.
    Film.; Neumann-Viertel, Elisabeth, 1900-1994; Bolváry, Géza von, 1897-1961
    - Original Recording (Box 9, Audiocassette 15)
      Tape Label: Side A "3.TEIL E. Neumann-Viertel 6.5.88" Side B: "4. TEIL 'Das Lied ist aus' 13.5.88"
      Translation Side A "Part 3: E. (Elisabeth) Neuman-Viertel May 6, 1988" Side B "Part 4: 'The Song Is Ended' May 13, 1988"
    - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 113, Cd 10:31)
  - Gauz Ich Daheim be Edith Kramer, July 11, 2003
    Recording begins with a brief piece of music and introduction. This is followed by a woman speaking in German about New York City. Possibly a radio program.
    - Original Recording (Box 9, Audiocassette 16)
    - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 113, Cd 10:32)
  - Austrian Heritage Collection Oral History Interview with Edith Kramer, April 13, 2005
    Austrian Heritage Collection oral history interview with Edith Kramer conducted on April 13, 2005.
    - Original Recording (Box 9, Audiocassette 17)
    - Original Recording (Box 9, Audiocassette 18)
    - Access Copies (Box Shared University Archives 113, Cd 10:29-10:30)
  - Quality And Inner Satisfaction: Revisiting The Importance Of Quality In Art And Art Therapy, November 2001
    Edith Kramer does not appear on this recording, which represents a plenary presentation at the annual conference for the American Art Therapy Association. Her lecture is read by the other participants. Participants include Susan Ainlay Anand and Lani A. Gerity. The tape was produced by the American Art Therapy Association, Inc.
    - Original Recording (Box 9, Audiocassette 19)
    - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 113, Cd 10:33)
  - Cultural Humility: Recognizing Wisdom, Hope, and Beauty in the Cultural Fringes, 2002
    This recording represents a panel discussion at the annual conference of the American Art Therapy Association, in which Edith Kramer participates. Other participants include Lani Gerity, Martha Haeseler, and Susan Anand. The tape was produced by the American Art Therapy Association, Inc.
    - Original Recording (Box 9, Audiocassette 20)
    - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 113, Cd 10:34)
  - Unexpected Gifts: A Discussion of Culture, Time and the Artist's Second Wind, 2000; 1 audiocassettes (Box 9, Cassette 21)
  - Practicum on making a career in art therapy, undated
    - Original Recording (Box 9, Audiocassette 23)
    - Original Recording (Box 9, Audiocassette 24)
    - Original Recording (Box 9, Audiocassette 25)
    - Original Recording (Box 9, Audiocassette 26)
    - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 113, Cd 10:25)
  - "Elena", 29 October 2009; 1 CD-ROM (Box 9, Disc 27)
- Series V: Artwork, 1916-2000; 8.75 Linear Feet In 52 custom portfolios, 6 oversize flat boxes, 2 manuscript boxes, 1 half manuscript box, 4 flat file folders, and 14 large artworks.
  This series includes two sub-series: Subseries A. Artwork by Edith Kramer; Subseries B. Artwork Created During Art Therapy. Materials in subseries A are grouped by medium and listed chronologically within those groupings. Subseries B has not been arranged by an archivist.
  Series V. consists of artwork created by Edith Kramer throughout her life as well as artwork created by her patients in the course of art therapy. As an artist, Kramer worked with a variety of media and this series includes oil and watercolor paintings; collages; drawings in ink, pencil, and charcoal; prints made using multiple techniques; and sculpture. Kramer created mosaic murals for the Spring St. and Union Square subway stations in New York City and this series includes planning documentation and a tile sample, as well as drawings of subway stations, trains, and riders.
  This series also includes art created by Kramer and her patients during the course of art therapy. The patient-created artworks in this series were primarily made at the Wiltwyck School for Boys, a residential treatment facility in Esopus, New York.
  In all cases, titles in brackets are descriptions of untitled works.
  - Sub-Series A: Artwork by Edith Kramer, 1916-1993
    Sub-Series A contains examples of Edith Kramer's artwork. These works highlight Kramer's development as an artist and her work in a variety of mediums, including sculpture, oil paintings, watercolors, collages, and pencil sketches. Of particular note is a sketchbook that includes pencil drawings inspired by the French Revolution that Kramer completed as a child. Many of the images depict industrial settings, subway stations or riders, and landscapes. Also included within the collection are a number of self-portraits completed at various ages. This series also encompasses sketches she completed of her fellow employees at the machine shop where she worked during World War II. This subseries also includes one portrait of Kramer at an easel; it is the only artwork in the subseries that was not created by Kramer.
    Two sketchbooks include protected health information (PHI); these have been foldered and labeled as restricted.
    - Girl Drawing -- oil on canvas, 1937; cuid264 (Item MC.215.cuid264)
    - Landscape with Haystack -- oil on canvas, 1938; cuid260 (Item MC.215.cuid260)
    - Cathedral of Ameins -- oil on canvas, 1949; cuid263 (Item MC.215.cuid263)
    - Mountain Larch -- oil on canvas, 1975; cuid259 (Item MC.215.cuid259)
    - Larches in Fog -- oil on canvas, 1980; cuid261 (Item MC.215.cuid261)
    - Self portrait -- oil on canvas, 1983; cuid265 (Item MC.215.cuid265)
    - [faces] -- oil on canvas, Undated; cuid258 (Item MC.215.cuid258)
    - Mountain Larches -- oil on canvas, Undated; cuid257 (Item MC.215.cuid257)
    - Railway Track in Prague -- oil on canvas, Undated; cuid262 (Item MC.215.cuid262, Item 6)
    - Collage, 1941; cuid266 (Item MC.215.cuid266)
    - Forsythe Park with Trees -- collage, 1969 (Flat-file-folder 1)
      Collage with paper and newsprint measuring 38 1/4" high by 42 1/4" wide.
    - Subway Illustrations, 1945-1998 (Box 14, Folder 4, 6, 11, Box 13, Folder 6, 15, 16, Flat-file-folder 6, Flat-file-folder 4)
      34 illustrations show subway stations, trains, and passengers. Stations pictured include 86th St. Station, 134th St. Station, Borough Hall, and Union Square Station. Illustrations are rendered in pencil, ink, color pencil, and watercolor.
    - Mosaic mural proposal for Chambers Street Station poster, 1993 (Flat-file-folder 6)
    - Mosaic Tile Sample Proposal for Chambers Street Station, 1993 (Box 12)
    - [construction] -- watercolor, 1947 (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - [New Jersey Turnpike] -- watercolor, 1953 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - [landscapes] -- watercolor, 1953; 1982 (Flat-file-folder 5, Box 17, Folder 5)
    - Petrified River, Weiderkar Austria -- watercolors, 1978, 1981 (Flat-file-folder 5)
    - [mountains and forest] -- watercolor, Undated (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - [seascape] -- watercolor, Undated (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Self Portrait -- pastel on paper, Undated
      Custodial History
      As of October 2023, this item is missing.
    - The French Revolution: A Homemade Storyboard, 1930 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Memoiren Eines Arztes (Memoirs of a Physician) from Alexandre Dumas' Marie Antoinette Romances -- ink on paper, ca. 1930s (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Machinist Drawings -- ink on paper, 1943-1948 (Box 13, Folder 11, 14, Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Cathedral d'Amiens Paris -- ink on paper, 1948 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - [park benches] -- ink on paper, Undated (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - [plant in vase] -- ink on paper, Undated
    - [plant] -- ink on paper, Undated
    - Carrot Top in Pot -- ink on paper, Undated
    - A Frieze of Pinto Bean Sprouts -- ink on paper, Undated
    - [flowers] -- ink on paper, Undated (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - Sketchbooks, circa 1916-2014 (Box 10, Box 18, Box 19)
      Conditions Governing Access
      Sketchbooks in box 19 contain protected health information and are restricted. Please contact university-archives@nyu.edu.
    - [figures/faces] -- pencil on paper, March 1937 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - [girl at table] -- pencil on paper, 1937 (Box 13, Folder 14)
    - Self portrait -- pencil on paper, 1937 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - [study of hands] and [portrait of Fridl Dicker] -- pencil sketches, 1937 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - [medieval figure with sword] -- pencil on paper, ca. 1937-1938 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - [sleeper] -- pencil on paper, 1938 (Box 13, Folder 8)
      Separated Materials
      This item received conservation treatment. Conservation documention is available upon request; please ask for Conservation ID number: 11-228l.
    - [girl reading] -- pencil on paper, 1938 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - [study with central seated figure] -- pencil and colored pencil on paper, 1938 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - [old couple] -- pencil on paper, 1940 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - 96th Street -- pencil and colored pencil drawing, 1950 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Study of Death of the Virgin, Insbruck -- pencil on paper, 1980 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - St. Lorenz, Verona -- pencil and colored media, 1985 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - [5 partial figures] -- pencil on paper, undated (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - [battle scene] -- pencil on paper, undated (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - [church window] -- pencil on paper, Undated (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - [figures on horseback] -- pencil on paper, undated (Box 13, Folder 14)
    - [nativity scene] -- pencil on paper, Undated (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - [seated figure with sword] -- pencil on paper, Undated (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - [ship] -- pencil on paper, Undated (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - [smiling girl] -- pencil on paper, undated (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - [statue of bearded figure] -- pencil on paper, Undated (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - [sleeping person] -- pencil on paper, Undated (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - Studies of Caravaggio paintings -- pencil on paper, Undated (Box 13, Folder 8, 9)
    - [study of sculpture from St. Stephen's Cathedral, Vienna] -- pencil on paper, Undated (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - [study of Madonna and Child sculpture] -- pencil on paper, Undated (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - [tree and rocks] -- pencil and colored pencil, Undated (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - [woman knitting] -- pencil on paper, Undated (Box 13, Folder 14)
    - Untitled group of notes and sketches, Undated (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - Allan Street -- Silverpoint on paper (Box 13, Folder 14)
    - [bocce courts] -- silverpoint on paper, Undated (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - [portrait of girl] -- silverpoint on paper, undated (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - [forest] -- intaglio print, 1954 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - [bridge] -- intaglio print, 1959 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - [man on stoop] -- intaglio print, 1959 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - [sleeping man on sidewalk] -- intaglio print, Undated (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - [pond with flora] -- relief print, undated (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - [machinery] -- relief print with silver leaf, Undated (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - [seascapes] -- woodcut prints, Undated (Box 13, Folder 3, 8)
    - [dinosaur fossil in museum] -- print, 1946 (Flat-file-folder 3)
    - [trees] -- photostat, Undated (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - [figure] -- charcoal on paper, undated (Flat-file-folder 7)
    - [portrait of a boy] -- charcoal on paper, undated (Flat-file-folder 1)
    - [squiggle] -- charcoal on paper, ca. 1930's (Flat-file-folder 2)
    - [Woman on bench] -- sculpture, Undated; cuid267 (Item MC.215.cuid267)
    - [People and trees] -- sculpture, Undated; cuid268 (Item MC.215.cuid268)
    - [Woman in bathtub] -- sculpture, Undated; cuid269 (Item MC.215.cuid269)
    - Ceramic pitcher with figures and trees, Undated; cuid270 (Item MC.215.cuid270)
    - [portrait of Edith Kramer at easel] -- woodcut print, 1981 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Sub-Series B: Artwork Created During Art Therapy, 1951-2000
    All artworks in this subseries were created during art therapy with Edith Kramer. The majority were created by patients, but some were created by Kramer as examples to show patients. Titles in brackets are descriptions of untitled works.
    Biographical
    Over the course of her career Edith Kramer worked as an art therapist at various institutions in the New York City metro area.
    Kramer worked at the Wiltwyck School for Boys in the 1940s and 1950s. This school was founded by the Episcopal City Mission Society in 1936 as a school and residential treatment facility for Black boys who were diverted from the juvenile justice system. In 1942, the Episcopal City Mission Society announced it could no longer financially support Wiltwyck. At this time group of concerned citizens, including Eleanor Roosevelt, recognized the value of Wiltwyck and banded together to fund the school and reorganize it under the State Department of Social Welfare. After the reorganization the school was non-secular and racially integrated, and in 1953 Wiltwyck began to accept students with emotional disabilities.1
    After leaving Wiltwyck, Kramer worked as an art therapist at the Leak and Watts Children's Home, the Turtle Bay Music School, the Guild School of the Jewish Guild for the Blind, and the Albert Einstein College of Medicine, Department of Child Psychiatry.